<metadata>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
<pubdate>2008</pubdate>
<title>USGS High Resolution Orthoimage USNG 19TCG300905, Boston, Massachusetts</title>
<geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>Urban Area Orthoimagery</sername>
<issue>0.1</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Sioux Falls, SD</pubplace>
<publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>The data obtained through The National Map Seamless Server is considered to be the "best available" data from USGS.  Historical data and other data may be obtained by contacting Customer Services, Earth Resources Observation &amp; Science Center, at 1-800-252-4547.

PLEASE NOTE:  The imagery is For Official Use Only (FOUO),  meaning these agencies can share the imagery among their Federal agency partners, and with State and local governments in the event of an emergency.</othercit>
<onlink>http://seamless.usgs.gov</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>"The primary digital orthophoto is a 15cm GSD resolution with tiles measuring 1500 x 1500 meters cast on the UTM Coordinate System Zone 19N on the North American Datum of 1983 (NAD83). The aerial photography used to create the digital images was flown on the 15th, 16th, and 17th of April 2008."  The original metadata were imported and updated for display through The National Map Seamless Server at &lt;http://seamless.usgs.gov&gt;    The naming convention is based on the USNG, taking the coordinates of the SW corner of the orthoimage.   Chip-level metadata are provided in XML format.

PLEASE NOTE:  The imagery is For Official Use Only (FOUO),  meaning these agencies can share the imagery among their Federal agency partners, and with States and local governments in the event of an emergency.</abstract>
<purpose>"The orthophotography was created for use by the USGS, NGA, and MassGIS."  High Resolution Orthoimagery provides a critical tool for those involved in development decisions such as resource managers and city planners.  The detailed focus of High Resolution Orthoimagery provides emergency responders critical information in determining the best evacuation routes, alternative routes and safe access to aid.   High Resolution Orthoimagery assists law enforcement personnel in determining the best locations to place surveillance cameras in high-traffic urban areas and popular attractions.  The data assists Federal, State and local emergency responders in planning for homeland security efforts.  This data also supports The National Map.</purpose>
<supplinf>Information in quotation marks is taken directly from the original metadata document.</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>200804</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>ground condition</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>Irregular</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<bounding>
<westbc>-71.0643934107998</westbc>
<eastbc>-71.0457514058465</eastbc>
<northbc>42.3616936900715</northbc>
<southbc>42.3485196129005</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>digital spatial data</themekey>
<themekey>0.15 meter orthoimage</themekey>
<themekey>rectified image</themekey>
<themekey>orthophoto</themekey>
<themekey>natural color orthophoto</themekey>
<themekey>orthoimage</themekey>
<themekey>image map</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>ISO 19115 Category</themekt>
<themekey>imageryBaseMapsEarthCover</themekey>
<themekey>010</themekey>
<themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
<themekey>008</themekey>
<themekey>location</themekey>
<themekey>013</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>U.S. Department of Commerce, 1995, Countries, dependencies, areas of special sovereignty, and their principal administrative divisions, Federal Information Processing Standard 10-4,): Washington, D.C., National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
<placekey>United States</placekey>
<placekey>U.S.</placekey>
<placekey>US</placekey>
</place>
<place>
<placekt>U.S. Department of Commerce, 1987, Codes for the identification of the States, the District of Columbia and the outlying areas of the United States, and associated areas (Federal Information Processing Standard 5-2): Washington, D.C., National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
<placekey>MA</placekey>
</place>
<place>
<placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
<placekey>Boston</placekey>
<placekey>Massachusetts</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<accconst>The  imagery is For Official Use Only (FOUO),  meaning these agencies can share the imagery among their Federal agency partners, and with State and local governments in the event of an emergency.</accconst>
<useconst>There is no guarantee of warranty concerning the accuracy of the data.  Users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since this data set was collected and that some parts of this data may no longer represent actual surface conditions.  Users should not use this data for critical applications without a full awareness of it's limitations.  Acknowledgement of the originating agencies would be appreciated in products derived from these data.  Any user who modifies the data is obligated to describe the types of modifications they perform.  User specifically agrees not to misrepresent the data, nor to imply that changes made were approved or endorsed by the U.S. Geological Survey.  Please refer to http://www.usgs.gov/privacy.html for the USGS disclaimer.  See Access_Constraints above.</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Customer Services Representative</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>USGS Earth Resources Observation &amp; Science Center</address>
<address>47914 252nd Street</address>
<city>Sioux Falls</city>
<state>SD</state>
<postal>57198-0001</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>605/594-6151</cntvoice>
<cntvoice>1-800-252-4547</cntvoice>
<cnttdd>605/594-6933</cnttdd>
<cntfax>605/594-6589</cntfax>
<cntemail>custserv@usgs.gov</cntemail>
<hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M - F (-6h CST/-5h CDT GMT)</hours>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<datacred>Massachusetts Geographic Information System (MassGIS), U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency (NGA) and Fugro Earthdata, Inc.</datacred>
<secinfo>
<secsys>FOUO</secsys>
<secclass>Restricted</secclass>
<sechandl>The imagery is For Official Use Only (FOUO),  meaning these agencies can share the imagery among their Federal agency partners, and with State and local governments in the event of an emergency.</sechandl>
</secinfo>
<native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.1.0.722</native>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>Radiometry is verified by visual inspection of the digital orthophoto.  Slight systematic radiometric differences may exist between adjacent orthoimage files; these are due primarily to differences in source image capture dates and sun angles along flight lines.  These differences can be observed in an image's general lightness or darkness when it is compared to adjacent orthoimage file coverages. Tonal balancing may be performed over a group of images during the mosaicking process which may serve to lighten or darken adjacent images for better color tone matching.</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>Logical consistency is implicit in the raster image data structure. Source imagery is cloud free.</logic>
<complete>"The following software is used for validation of the imagery and surface modeling 1. Aerotriangulation - ISTAR 2. Digital Orthophotography - ISTAR 3. Bentley - MicroStation 4. ISTAR 5. ZI - OrthoPro 6. ESRI - ArcInfo 7. ERDAS Imagine 8. TerraScan 9. EarthData Proprietary software 10. Adobe - Photoshop 11. GPrO.  Orthoimages are visually inspected for completeness to ensure that no gaps or image misplacements exist within and between adjacent images. These images are derived by mosaicking multiple images to ensure complete coverage. Source imagery is cloud free. Photography was flown during leaf-off in deciduous vegetation regions. Coastal areas and international boundary regions may have areas without images (void areas) in parts of the coverage. These void areas have a radiometric value of either zero (black) or 128 (uniform gray)."</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>The relative accuracy is assembled by comparing rectified images generated from adjacent strips of imagery. The absolute accuracy is assessed by measuring the ground control points in the rectified image against the actual surveyed co-ordinate position. The testing is for overall accuracy.</horizpar>
</horizpa>
<vertacc>
<vertaccr>There is no vertical accuracy component to orthophotography</vertaccr>
</vertacc>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
<pubdate>2008</pubdate>
<title>imagery</title>
<geoform>raster digital data</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>Urban Area Orthoimagery</sername>
<issue>0.1</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Sioux Falls, SD</pubplace>
<publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
</pubinfo>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>raster digital data</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>200804</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>imagery</srccitea>
<srccontr>Source imagery for tile production</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<procstep>
<procdesc>"The digital orthophotography is comprised of a 24 bit, natural color RGB bands plus a CIR band, 0.15 meter pixel resolution ground orthos for the Boston Upgrade of the USGS project. The ISTAR process was used in the generation of the orthoimagery covering all project tiles. The initial radiometric adjustments were performed on the imagery for each flight line attempting to reach the best possible histogram. The rectification process was then run using the processed DSM surface and the radiometrically balanced imagery on each flight line. The quicklook (reduced resolution rectification) of each flight line exported out of ISTAR. A second set of radiometric adjustments were made using Earthdata proprietary tools. The radiometrically balanced imagery was then re-imported into the ISTAR system and the histogram from the quicklook was applied to the full resolution imagery. Mosaic lines were placed, joining the ADS40 imagery strips. In initial QA/QC was performed by the technician to ensure that the mosaic lines were appropriately placed and that there was appropriate imagery coverage. The final imagery data set is removed from the ISTAR environment in a process called "packaging" where the individual tiles are created. All data processing in the ISTAR system is performed in UTM Zone 19N meters; it is during packaging that final datum and projection are defined. The created tiles are reviewed again for anomalies and interactive radiometric adjustment applied where needed. QA/QC was performed looking for anomalies, smears and other indications of problems within the digital Orthophoto creation process, interactive radiometric adjustment applied where needed. Two additional radiometric adjustments are applied to the completed orthos in Adobe Photoshop. The first is a sharpening mask filter; this filter is used to help increase sharpness of a digital image. The basis for this filter is to locate pixels that differ in value from surrounding pixels by the threshold specified. It then increases the pixels' contrast by the value identified. For neighboring pixels specified by the threshold, the lighter pixels get even lighter and the darker pixels get even darker based on the specified amount. The changes made maintained the integrity of the original histogram curve. The final digital ortho product was GEOTIFF files. All data was delivered on external hard drives."</procdesc>
<procdate>200805</procdate>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>The original metadata were imported and updated for display through The National Map Seamless Server at &lt;http://seamless.usgs.gov&gt;    The naming convention is based on the USNG, taking the coordinates of the SW corner of the orthoimage.   Chip-level metadata are provided in XML format.</procdesc>
<procdate>200811</procdate>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Customer Service Representative</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>USGS Earth Resources Observation &amp; Science Center</address>
<address>47914 252nd Street</address>
<city>Sioux Falls</city>
<state>SD</state>
<postal>57198-0001</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>605-594-6151</cntvoice>
<cntvoice>1-800-252-4547</cntvoice>
<cnttdd>605-594-6933</cnttdd>
<cntfax>605-594-6589</cntfax>
<cntemail>custserv@usgs.gov</cntemail>
<hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M - F (-6h CST/-5h CDT GMT)</hours>
<cntinst>The USGS point of contact is for questions relating only to the data display and download from this web site.</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<direct>Raster</direct>
<rastinfo>
<rasttype>Pixel</rasttype>
<rowcount>10000</rowcount>
<colcount>10000</colcount>
<vrtcount>1</vrtcount>
</rastinfo>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<gridsys>
<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
<utm>
<utmzone>19</utmzone>
<transmer>
<sfctrmer>0.999600</sfctrmer>
<longcm>-69.000000</longcm>
<latprjo>0.000000</latprjo>
<feast>500000.000000</feast>
<fnorth>0.000000</fnorth>
</transmer>
</utm>
</gridsys>
<planci>
<plance>row and column</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>0.150000</absres>
<ordres>0.150000</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
<ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257222</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
<vertdef>
<altsys>
<altdatum>North American Vertical Datum of 1988</altdatum>
<altres>1.00000</altres>
<altunits>meters</altunits>
<altenc>Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc>
</altsys>
</vertdef>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>For color-infrared and natural color DOQs, a digital number from zero to 255 will be assigned to each pixel but that number will refer to a color look-up table which will contain the RGB red, blue and green (RGB) values, each from zero to 255, for that digital number. Areas where the rectification process is incomplete due to incomplete data (i.e., lack of elevation data, gaps), are represented with the numeric value of zero.</eaover>
<eadetcit>U.S. Department of the Interior, U.S. Geological Survey, 1999, Standards for Digital Orthoimagery: Reston, VA</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Customer Services Representative</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>USGS Earth Resources Observation &amp; Science Center</address>
<address>47914 252nd Street</address>
<city>Sioux Falls</city>
<state>SD</state>
<postal>57198-0001</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>605/594-6151</cntvoice>
<cntvoice>1-800-252-4547</cntvoice>
<cnttdd>605/594-6933</cnttdd>
<cntfax>605/594-6589</cntfax>
<cntemail>custserv@usgs.gov</cntemail>
<hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M - F (-6h CST/-5h CDT GMT)</hours>
<cntinst>The USGS point of contact is for questions relating only to the data display and download from this web site.  For questions regarding data content and quality, refer to the original processor.

PLEASE NOTE:  The  imagery is For Official Use Only (FOUO),  meaning these agencies can share the imagery among their Federal agency partners, and with State and local governments in the event of an emergency.</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Downloadable Data (RESTRICTED- For Official Use Only)</resdesc>
<distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the USGS, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the USGS regarding the use of the data on any other system, nor does the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  Data may have been compiled from various outside sources.  Spatial information may not meet National Map Accuracy Standards.  This information may be updated without notification. The USGS shall not be liable for any activity involving these data, installation, fitness of the data for a particular purpose, its use, or analyses results.</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>TIFF</formname>
<formvern>ArcGIS 9.1</formvern>
<formspec>Raster</formspec>
<transize>0.001</transize>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://seamless.usgs.gov</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
<accinstr>The URL  &lt;http://seamless.usgs.gov&gt; provides a map interface that allows for data downloads within a customer defined area of interest. Zoom tools are available that can be used to investigate areas of interest on the map interface. The download tool allows the customer to capture layers from the map, utilizing The National Map Seamless Server process for downloading. A request summary page is then generated with the download layers listed. By clicking the "download" button on the summary page, a zipped file will be generated that can be saved on the customer's computer. The file can then be unzipped and imported into various user software applications.</accinstr>
<oncomp>Not available for dissemination</oncomp>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
<turnarnd>Variable</turnarnd>
</stdorder>
<techpreq>ESRI ArcGIS Suite and/or Arc/Info software or equivalent GIS processing software and supporting operating systems.</techpreq>
<availabl>
<timeinfo>
<rngdates>
<begdate>2008</begdate>
<enddate>unknown</enddate>
</rngdates>
</timeinfo>
</availabl>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20081111</metd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Customer Services Representative</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>USGS Earth Resources Observation &amp; Science Center</address>
<address>47914 252nd Street</address>
<city>Sioux Falls</city>
<state>SD</state>
<postal>57198-0001</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>605/594-6151</cntvoice>
<cntvoice>1-800-252-4547</cntvoice>
<cnttdd>605/594-6933</cnttdd>
<cntfax>605/594-6589</cntfax>
<cntemail>custserv@usgs.gov</cntemail>
<hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M - F (-6h CST/-5h CDT GMT)</hours>
<cntinst>The above is the contact information for the USGS Earth Resources Observation &amp; Science Center in Sioux Falls, SD.  This is the digital data storage and distribution center for the USGS.</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
<mettc>local time</mettc>
<metac>None</metac>
<metuc>None</metuc>
<metsi>
<metscs>None</metscs>
<metsc>Unclassified</metsc>
<metshd>None</metshd>
</metsi>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink>
<metprof>ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof>
</metextns>
</metainfo>
</metadata>
